《哥谭》前情提要
Previously on Gotham...
你有没有遇到多尔蒂警官
You haven't, by chance, seen Officer Dougherty?
我们昨晚约好一起吃晚饭的
We were... supposed to have dinner last night.
他没来  这也不奇怪
He didn't show-- no surprise--
但今天他也没来上班
um, but I haven't seen him today.
我也没见到他
Me neither.
芭芭拉  我们这是为了你
Barbara, we're doing this for you.
他死了
He's dead?
嗯  他死了
Yeah. He's dead.
没事了
It's gonna be okay.
布鲁斯  你父亲是个真正清心寡欲之人
Bruce, your father was a true Stoic.
他最好的一面不为人所知
He kept his best self hidden.
你父亲是个好人
Your father was a good man.
但好人也有秘密
But even good men have secrets.
你很顽固  詹姆斯  跟你父亲一样
You have a hard head, James, just like your father.
哥谭现在是在刀口上
Gotham is on a knife edge.
但我绝不会束手旁观看着它崩溃
But I won't let it fall apart without a fight.
刚刚得到消息  法尔科内城里
Just got wind of three separate attacks
三处不同地点的生意遭到袭击
on Falcone businesses in different parts of town.
是马罗尼干的
It's Maroni.
枪战开始了
We're in a shooting war.
本字幕由 YYeTs 人人影视 原创翻译
[WEB&BD版美剧字幕精编者]再加工制成
本人由衷感谢原译作者的无私奉献  并保留译作者的信息
如需其它剧集字幕  请登陆新浪微博（http://weibo.com/MJZM100）
或发邮件索取 lj20090303@163.com
Reginamoon    DustD    charcie    Silence
爵士年代蓬蓬裙    木浅薰    草草
Kallen   艹明   最可爱的小胖子
饿得慌
宝宝
草草
早上好  孩子们
Good morning, child.
我们不是孩子
We ain't children,
而且...现在也不是早上
and... it ain't morning.
很快就是了
Oh, it will be soon.
崭新的一天
A brand-new day.
两周后
黑帮战争在哥谭市愈演愈烈
The gang war rages on here in Gotham.
没人知道是什么引发了这场血腥的地盘大战
No one knows what set this bloody turf war off,
但大家普遍认为这是长久以来
but it is commonly believed to be the result
萨尔维多・马罗尼和卡麦・法尔科内的
of the longtime power struggle between Salvatore Maroni
权力之争造成的
and Carmine Falcone.
作为宿敌  这两位经常...
Longtime enemies, these men have often come to blows...
还在秘密是不是  少爷
Still looking for secrets, are we, sir?
还是只是在砸东西
Or just breaking stuff?
找秘密
Secrets.
这样好吗
I don't know.
整座城市都疯掉了
Whole city's going doolally around us.
街头正在打仗
I mean, there's a bloody war on the streets...
但你却在这里操心你的老父亲
and you're in here worrying about your poor old dad.
的确
Yes, I am.
假如你父亲真有不为人知的生活
If your father had a secret life--
容我说一句  他没有
which I hasten to add, he didn't--
那我肯定会知道的  是不是
I'd know about it, wouldn't I?
他是个稳重勤勉的人
A sober, diligent man he was.
从不出去寻欢作乐
Never out gallivanting.
每晚都回家  准时准点
Home every night, like clockwork,
就在这间屋子里工作
working, in this very room.
是的  我记得
Yes, I remember.
他工作的时候不许我去吵他
I wasn't allowed to disturb him while he was working.
任何人都不许
Nobody was.
古典乐...
Classical music...
他会放好几个小时
he would play for hours.
没错
That's right.
妈妈和我会读书或者玩棋类游戏
Mom and I would read books or play board games
直到他工作完
until he was done.
我记得
I remember.
我曾试图溜进去看他
I tried to sneak in to see him,
但门是锁着的
but the door was locked.
当时门是不是总是锁着的  阿尔弗雷德
Was the door always locked, Alfred?
是的  我想是的  在他工作的时候
Yeah, well, I suppose so, when he was working.
但是为什么呢
Why, though?
为什么要锁门
Why lock the door?
装门就是用来锁的  是不是
That's what doors are for, isn't it?
就在这里
It's in here.
就在这间房子里
It's in this room.
我父亲的秘密  就在这间房子里
My father's secret, it's in this room.
我知道
I know it.
I know it!
你好呀  小姑娘
Hello, young lady.
我喜欢你的样子
I like your style.
哥谭
第一季第二十二集[季终]
把法尔科内的人关在一间牢房里
Hey, put Falcone's guys in one cell,
马罗尼的关在另一间
and Maroni's in another.
进去
Get in there!
抓住他
Get him!
进去吧
Get in there!
外面
Outside!
是卡茨警官吧
Officer Katz, right?
是  长官  格里芬・卡茨
Yes, sir, Katz, Griffin.
提个建议  卡茨
Word of advice, Katz.
我是注定要完蛋的人
I'm a dead duck around here.
黑帮战争一冷却下来
Brass are gonna fire me just as soon as
上头就会马上开除我
this gang war cools off.
所以别朝我敬礼
So don't salute me.
只会显得你傻
Makes you look like a rube.
-警探  -汤普金斯医生
- Detective. - Dr. Thompkins.
吉姆
Jim.
谢谢你来看我
Thanks for coming to see me.
看到你没事我就放心了
It's good to see you looking so well.
我是挺好
I am well.
比之前好多了
Much better.
是啊
Yes.
没错  这是你最后一次检查了
You are. This is your last checkup.
你身体上的伤已经痊愈
You are all healed physically.
但你需要接受心理创伤治疗
But you need to get some trauma counseling.
医生  我很开心
Doc, I'm happy.
我高兴我还活着
I am happy to be alive.
所以  吉姆  我走之前
Which is why, Jim, I didn't want to leave
想正式向你道谢
without saying thank you properly.
谢谢你救了我的命
Thank you for saving my life.
能救你我很高兴
I was glad to do it.
基恩小姐
Miss Kean...
心理创伤治疗  你真的很需要
trauma counseling, like, yesterday.
我可以推荐几个人给你
I have several recommendations for you.
-医生  真的  我很好  -你一点也不好
- Really, Doc, I am fine. - You're not fine.
你经历了那些事  不可能会好
After what you've been through, nobody would be fine.
好啊  如果你为我治疗就行
Fine. If you will be my counselor.
还要去我家会诊
And we do it at my place.
不行  我接受过创伤治疗训练
No. I have some trauma training,
但这不是我的专长
but it's not my area of focus.
我喜欢你
I like you.
我可以对你敞开话匣
Hey, I can talk to you.
求你了
Please?
好吧
Okay.
说定了
Deal.
谢谢你
Thank you.
好了  给你们最后一次警告
All right, last warning to all of you!
别放了那家伙
Don't free that guy!
吉姆  你看新闻了吗
Hey, Jim, did you hear the news?
法尔科内阁下遭暗杀了
Don Falcone just got hit.
-吉姆  -怎么了
- Jim? - What?!
法尔科20分钟前遭暗杀了
Falcone got hit 20 minutes ago.
马罗尼的人炸掉了他的车
Maroni's boys blew up his car.
-他死了吗  -没有  他在医院呢
- He's dead? - No. He's at the hospital,
不过他也快死了
but he'll be dead soon enough.
听着  艾森说市政府和权贵都默许了暗杀
Listen, Essen said City Hall and the bigwigs okayed the hit.
他们转向支持马罗尼了
They switched their support to Maroni.
马罗尼  那个莽人
Maroni? That hothead?
他们觉得他能掌管这城市吗
They think he can run this city?
总得有人倒台
Someone had to go.
这场战争损害了生意
This war has been bad for business.
你好
Hello?
有人吗
Hello!
早上好  早上好
Good morning. Good morning.
企鹅  感谢上帝
Oh, Penguin, thank God.
把我弄出去
Get me out of here.
马罗尼的人马上就到了
Maroni's men will be here any minute.
是的  我想也是
Yes, I imagine so.
不能待太久
Mustn't stay long.
但是  我如果不亲自跟你道别
But... I knew I'd regret it if I didn't say
我一定会后悔的
good-bye to you in person.
是我干的  老朋友
It was me, old friend.
是我害了你
I did this to you.
我挑起了战争
I started the war.
从见到你的第一天起  我就开始筹划你的结局
From the day I met you, I was planning your end.
很遗憾要在这种
I'm sorry it has to be in this...
肮脏的小地方结束  但是...
squalid little corner, but...
这就是人生
...c'est la vie.
为什么
Why?
不是针对你  我向你保证  先生
Nothing personal, I assure you, sir.
你一直是位睿智的导师
You have been a wise mentor
还是位好朋友
and a good friend,
但是
but...
生意总得摆在第一位
business must come first.
我要取代你的位置  老头
I'm gonna take your place, old man.
我要成为哥谭之王
And I'm gonna be the King of Gotham.
你
You?
绝不可能
Never.
你会下地狱的
You're going to burn in Hell.
我确实有这担忧
I do worry about that.
不过你先请了
But you first,
老朋友
old friend.
你先
You first.
不许动
Nobody move!
走开
Walk away!
闭嘴
Shut up.
你们俩都因为谋杀未遂被捕了
You're both under arrest for attempted murder.
你没听说吗
Didn't you hear?
法尔科内已经正式下台了
Falcone is out by official decree.
大家都同意了
Everyone agreed.
我听说了
I heard.
那放了我吧  吉姆
So, release me, Jim.
站在赢家这边
Get on the winning side.
什么赢家
Winning side, my ass.
马罗尼就是个白痴  他替代不了我
Maroni's a fool. He can't replace me.
他上台会有不计其数的人反对他
A thousand rivals will jump up to challenge him.
会引起一片混战
There'll be civil war.
如果我现在死  哥谭就会分崩离析
If I die now, Gotham falls apart.
我同意  那你能扭转局势吗
I agree, but can you turn things around?
你能夺回控制权吗
Can you take back control?
当然
Of course.
只要去我的安全屋躲两天
Two days at my safe house.
我需要两天布置行动
I need two days to make some moves,
然后我就能把马罗尼和那些叛徒扒皮抽筋
and I'll skin Maroni and those disloyal scum like rabbits.
醒醒吧  拿破仑大人
Wake up, Napoleon!
马罗尼的人马上
Maroni's louts are minutes away
就要赶到这里  割断你的喉咙
from coming here and cutting your throat,
问题是  吉姆  他们也
and the thing is, Jim, they aren't very fond
不是很喜欢我  所以说真的
of me, either, so, seriously,
你得赶紧放开我  吉姆
you need to uncuff me-- Jim?!
吉姆  你跑哪里去了
Jim, where the hell'd you run off to?
哈维
Harv,
我和法尔科内在医院
I'm in the hospital with Falcone.
这里一个人都没有
There's nobody here.
当然不会有  你跑那干什么去了
No kidding. What the hell are you doing there?
赶紧出来
You gotta get out now.
他们肯定会回去解决他的
They'll be coming back to finish him off.
我知道  马上就要到了
Yeah. Any moment now.
除非我先救他出去
Unless I get him out of here.
吉姆  吉姆  吉姆
Jim, Jim, Jim, Jim.
我需要你帮忙
I could use some help.
没门  你是疯了吗
No way. Are you nuts?
他是坏人  但是坏人里最好的一个了
He's a bad man, but he's the best bad man we got.
如果法尔科内失去控制权
If Falcone loses control,
马罗尼太疯狂  控制不了哥谭
Maroni's too wild to run Gotham.
到时会一片混乱
There'll be anarchy.
有可能
Yeah, probably,
但法尔科内已经失去控制权了
but Falcone already lost control.
他会夺回来的
And he'll get it back.
你就是因为芭芭拉的事头脑不清楚
Listen, you're all twisted over what happened to Barbara.
你失去理智了
You're not thinking straight.
是啊  也许吧
Yeah. Maybe.
但反正我在这儿也混不下去了
But I'm done in this town anyhow.
还怕失去什么呢
What do I have to lose?
你的小命
Your life.
小命也不要了吗
How 'bout your life?
你在这里做什么
What the hell are you doing here?
不是跟你们都说好了吗
I thought the fix was in with you guys.
你能走路吗
Can you walk?
-勉强  -先把你弄出去
- If I have to. - Let's get you out of here--
我带你去你的安全屋
I'll take you to your safe house.
吉姆  我的朋友
Jim, my friend,
这么做是个天大的错误
you are making a terrible mistake.
我这么做是为了哥谭
I'm doing this for the city,
不是为了你
not you.
你是糟糕选择里最好的一个
You're the least worst option.
如果我觉得你夺不回控制权
If I didn't think you could take back control,
也不会救你
I'd let you die.
得先把话说清楚
Just so we're clear.
很清楚
We're clear.
你不能丢下我不管
You can't leave me here.
马罗尼的人会杀了我的
Maroni's men will kill me!
很可能
Possible.
不  不行  你逮捕了我们
No. No, you-you arrested us.
我们是你的责任
We are in your custody.
那倒是
That's true.
你欠我个人情  吉姆
You owe me a favor, Jim.
你欠我的
You owe me!
该死
Damn it.
詹姆斯・戈登
James Gordon!
戈登警探
Detective Gordon!
别杀他们
Don't kill 'em.
早安啊  各位
Morning, fellas.
有什么能帮你们的
What can I help you with?
当然  戈登
Yes, Gordon.
你又在错误的时间出现在错误的地点
As usual, wrong place, wrong time.
现在赶紧走
Go. Now.
干吗  让这些人杀掉卡麦・法尔科内吗
Why? So these men can kill Carmine Falcone?
这我不清楚
I have no knowledge of that.
快走
Go.
这是命令
That's an order.
你真是个耻辱  洛布
You're a disgrace, Loeb.
希望很快能看到你被绳之以法
I hope to see you behind bars very soon.
要么就横尸街头
Or dead.
都行
Whichever.
希望
Hope.
是给失败者的...
It's for losers...
吉姆
Jim.
留给你们了
He's all yours!
杀了他
Get him!
快  快
Move, move, move, move.
吉姆  吉姆  别开枪  是我
Jim! Jim! Don't shoot! It's me!
赶紧走吧  地下室有救护车
We gotta go-- There are ambulances in the basement.
你救的人呢
Where's your man?
这个嘛
About that.
咱们还得带上企鹅和吉尔兹
We got to take Penguin and Gilzean, too.
企鹅和吉尔兹
Penguin and Gilzean?
我以谋杀未遂罪逮捕了他们
I arrested 'em for attempted murder.
他们现在受我监管
They're in my custody.
我都不想跟你争了
I don't even want to argue with you.
来吧  咱们走  赶紧
Come on! Let's go! Go!
汤米  汤米
Tommy... Tommy!
老大  老大  小心
Boss! Boss! Look out!
趴下
Get down!
该死
Damn it.
我们究竟在找什么  布鲁斯少爷
What exactly are we looking for, Master Bruce?
等我找到了  就知道了
When I find it, I'll know.
没人知道这地方  对吧
Nobody knows about this place, right? Nobody?
没人  知道这地方的人都死了
Nobody. Anybody who did is dead.
这里很安全
We'll be safe here.
你们好啊
Hello.
干什么呢
What's up?
我知道  我知道
I know, I know.
这太令人震惊了
It's astonishing.
我有时都能把自己吓一跳
Sometimes I astonish myself.
我感觉
I feel like, uh,
这一切像一场梦
this is all a dream,
很快就会醒来
and I'm gonna wake up soon.
芭芭拉
Barbara,
你遭到绑架
you were abducted.
眼看着父母被杀
Your parents were killed in front of you.
没错  那是真的
Yeah. Yeah, that's real.
我说的是现在
I'm talking about this. Now. This...
现在是一场梦
This is the dream.
我会醒来
I'm gonna wake up
然后...
and...
发现他还活着...
he's still alive...
他会来找我
and he's coming for me.
我以为你死了
I thought for sure you were dead.
让我好好看看你
Let me look at you.
菲什
Fish?
真的是你吗
Is it real... It's really you?
是我  布奇  我回家了
It's... it's me, Butch. I'm home.
可怜的宝贝  他们对你干了什么
My poor baby. What did they do to you?
不是什么好事
Nothing good.
是他  老大
It's him, boss.
马罗尼阁下
Don Maroni.
没错
Yes.
毫发无伤
Alive and well.
这就说来话长了
That's a long story.
我们要谈谈
We need to talk.
我手上有你想要的东西
I have something you want.
他们没找到我的小刀
They didn't find my knife.
那就有救了
So we're saved then.
在我袜子里
It's in my sock.
如果你有机会  拉几个垫背的
If you get the chance, take some of them with us.
我尽量
I'll try.
你好啊
Hey, you.
塞琳娜  你在这儿干什么
Selina, what are you doing here?
就待着
Chillin'.
你呢
How 'bout you?
被绑住了
Kind of jammed up.
是啊
Yeah.
真是太糟了
That's too bad.
你这哑谜是"求救"的意思吗
That's mime for "Help us out here."
你要我毁掉最酷的一单活儿
And totally blow the coolest gig ever
就因为我们算是认识吗
just because we kinda, sorta know each other?
是吗
Right?
好啊  小伙子们
Hello, fellas.
卡麦
Carmine.
企鹅
Penguin.
没什么想说的吗
Nothing to share?
我倒是有件事
Well, I have a little something.
我刚和马罗尼达成了一桩不错的交易
I just made a sweet deal with Maroni.
他和我说  我可以拿回我所有的地盘
He just told me I could have all my territories back,
作为交换  我只要
and all I have to do in return...
把卡麦的脑袋拿给他
is give him Carmine's head.
菲什  我要去躺会儿
Uh, Fish, I-I need to go lie down.
你都对那可怜人干了什么  你这虐待狂
What did you do to that poor soul, you sadist?
我向你保证
I assure you...
你会
You will die
为布奇的事  慢慢地  痛苦地死去
a slow, painful death on account of Butch.
你也一样  卡麦
You, too, Carmine.
而你
You...
给你个痛快的
We'll keep it simple.
你呢
And you?
你不会有事
We're cool.
有任何疑问吗
Any questions?
你想怎么杀他们
How you gonna kill 'em?
我喜欢这丫头
I love this girl.
杰森看穿了我
Jason saw right through me.
他一见面就了解了我
He knew me instantly.
就好像我一丝不挂
Like I was naked.
很吓人
It was scary...
也令人兴奋
but thrilling.
而且
And...
说起来
aren't...
那些好男人不是都有些吓人吗
all the best guys a little scary?
我们第一次约会时  我就很怕吉姆・戈登
I was way more scared of Jim Gordon the first date we went on.
那么孔武有力
So butch and... stern.
那种男人通常都是暴脾气
That type, they-they often have a bad temper.
但吉姆是个好人
But Jim was a sweetie.
从未动过我一根手指
Never laid a finger on me.
挺令人惊讶的
It was kind of surprising.
他打过你吗
Does he ever hit you?
我  没有  为什么
Me? No. Why?
他为什么会打人呢
Wh-Why would he hit anyone?
怎么会打女人呢
Any woman?
你懂的
You know.
出于激情
Out of passion.
对不起  我并不是要窥探什么
I'm sorry, I didn't mean to pry.
只是我听说你和吉姆在约会
Only I heard you and Jim were dating.
没有
No.
是的  我们是约过几次
Y-Yes, we've been on a few dates.
对不起  我不知道你已经知道了
I'm sorry, I didn't think that you knew.
如果你觉得不舒服的话
If that makes you uncomfortable in any way...
没有  别傻了
No. Don't be silly.
我为你高兴
I, uh... I'm happy for you.
他真的是个好人
He's one of the good guys.
是啊
Yeah, he is.
饿了吗
Hey, you hungry?
他来了
So, there he is.
菲什  你个神秘  疯狂  美丽的小杀手
Fish, you mysterious, crazy, gorgeous killer, you.
爱死你了
I love ya.
抱一个
Come here.
这真是...
This...
真是太美好了
this is delicious.
终于啊
Finally.
你命真硬  老家伙
You're hard to kill, old man.
不
No.
是你的人太次了
Your people are second-rate.
穆尼女士  我有几句话要说
Miss Mooney, if I may, a brief word.
我知道我一定没命了
I know my life is forfeit.
所以我不是为自己  我是为了你
I speak not for my sake, but yours.
因为毕竟
Because... after all,
我还是爱你  敬重你的
I still love and respect you.
杀我无所谓
Kill me if you must,
但请留法尔科内一命
but keep Falcone alive.
他一死  你对马罗尼来说就毫无用处了
As soon as he's dead, Maroni has no use for you.
你就是个威胁  他会杀了你的
You are simply a threat. He will kill you.
是吗
You think?
他干吗要容下一山二虎
Why would he need another boss in town?
另一个对手
Another rival?
这你就错了  机灵鬼
That's where you're wrong, smart guy.
她不是对手
She's not a rival,
因为她不是老大
because she's not a boss.
她是二把手
She's an underboss.
二把手听命于人
An underboss takes orders.
而我不
I don't take orders.
我知道  我们没事
I know that. We're cool.
放松
Relax.
我很放松
I'm relaxed.
我觉得你没有  美女
I don't think you are, babes.
别叫我美女
Please don't call me babes.
看见没
You see?
还是紧张
Not relaxed.
美女  不是吧
Babes? Really?
这只是表示亲热
It's a term of endearment.
表示我喜欢你
It means I like you.
好吧
Fine.
我说错话了
I misspoke.
你不是二把手  你不是谁的"美女"
You're not an underboss and you're not a babe.
你自己说你是什么吧
You tell me what you are.
萨尔  我们是
What we are, Sal...
伙伴
...are partners.
随你吧
Whatever you want.
伙伴
Partners.
我是一号伙伴
I'm partner number one,
你是二号伙伴
and you're partner number two.
就是这样  对吧
That's the deal, right?
我是一号
I'm number one...
你是...
and you are...?
二号
Number two.
这就对啦
There you go.
简单的算术
Simple math.
一号  二号  美女  抱歉
One, two, babes. Oops. Sorry.
最后一次  我保证
That's the last time. I swear.
伙计们
Guys!
你们感受到这气氛了吗
Can you feel the buzz in the air?
这是胜利的气氛
That's victory.
是救赎  是力量
Redemption. Power!
等这老头一死  新的一天就将到来
When this old man dies, a new day begins.
我们将统治哥谭
We will rule Gotham.
我们将建立新朝代
We are building a dynasty.
我们将让这座城市唯命是从
We will whip this town like a rented mule.
是吧  美女
Right, babes?
别激动
Oh-ho, just... all right, relax.
我逗你玩呢
I'm kidding you.
不过  说真的
Guys, no, seriously.
别叫她"美女"
Don't call her "babes."
还是"亲亲"什么的
Or "toots" or what have you.
这是女权问题
It's a woman's lib thing.
我很放松
I am relaxed.
快走
Let's go!
芭芭拉  我们一直在兜圈子
Barbara, we've been circling around the subject,
但还没真正谈及发生在你身上的事
but haven't talked about what actually happened to you;
你经受的遭遇
wh-what was done to you.
小莱
Lee...
你是个好人
you're a nice lady.
我可以谈那些
I could go there,
但你恐怕不会想听的
but I'm not sure you want to go there with me.
别担心我
Don't worry about me.
吉姆对你说过我爱你吗
Has Jim told you he loves you?
-芭芭拉  -公平点
- Barbara... - Fair is fair.
我都把小秘密告诉你了
I'm telling you all my little secrets.
他还没说过
No, he hasn't.
但他会说的  对吧
But he will, though, won't he?
你觉得那一天要来了吗
You can feel it coming?
看看你啊
I mean, come on, look at you.
你又美丽  又聪慧  他当然爱你了
You're gorgeous and smart-- of course he loves you.
你爱他吗
Do you love him?
芭芭拉
Barbara...
告诉我到底发生了什么
Tell me what happened.
如果我们能冲到第七大道不被菲什的人发现
If we can get to 7th Avenue without being spotted by Fisher's people,
我们就可以安全回家了
we're home free.
-然后呢  -找个安全的地方  重新部署
- Then what? - We find a safe place, regroup.
马罗尼的死是你的运气
Maroni's death is a lucky break for you.
这口气真像个黑手党
Spoken like a true mafioso.
你说了  你是最不糟糕的选择
You're the least worst option, like you said.
没有了你  哥谭会分崩离析
Without you, the city falls apart.
是啊  我是说过  也可能真是这样
Yes, I said that, and it might be true,
但今天真的很漫长
but this has been a long day
我也有充足的时间
and I've had a long time
审视我所创造出来的世界
to look at this world I've created.
我不再干这些事了  我退出
I'm done with this business. I'm out.
我在南边有个可以隐退的地方
I've got a place down south I can go to.
对不起
I'm sorry.
You're sorry?
我知道  我让你失望了
I know. I'm letting you down.
我让哥谭失望了  我知道
I'm letting the city down. I know.
我听到了动静
Hey, I heard something.
这边
Yeah, flash it this way.
这里  这边来
Down here, down here!
好吧  B计划
Okay, plan B.
用灯照着
Keep the light up.
你在南边有隐退的地方
So you got a place down south, huh?
水边的好地方吗
Nice? On the water?
是的
Yes.
能给退役警察找份活儿干吗
Any work for beat-up old cops?
当然
Sure.
怎么样  吉姆
How's that sound, Jim?
海滩  阳光  钓钓鱼
Beaches, sunshine, fishing...
真不错
Yeah, tempting.
又见了
Hello again.
猫咬着舌头了  怎么不说话
Cat got your tongue?
太好了
Yes!
塞琳娜
Selena.
各位
Boys.
你们太棒了
Bless you.
你真厉害  菲什
Got to hand it to you, Fish.
太会打断表演了
You really know how to stop a show.
我忍不住  哈维  他惹我生气了
I couldn't help myself, Harvey, the man vexed me.
疯狂之举
Crazy move.
可能也是步好棋  走着瞧吧
Possibly a good move, too. We'll see.
战场形势不断变换
The battlefield is in flux.
说不定我会成为哥谭的新女王
You could be looking at the new Queen of Gotham.
恭喜你了  亲爱的
Congratulations, my dear.
我不干了  菲什
I'm quitting, Fish.
我退出
I'm out.
那么我是不用杀你了吗
Does this mean I don't have to kill you?
你要去个温暖的地方隐退  休息
You're gonna retire someplace warm, lay back,
读东西解闷吗
read your little funny papers?
-是这么想的  -嗯
- That was the thought. - Yeah.
想得美
Nice thought.
菲什
Fish!
不要  求你
Please, no.
菲什
Fish!
你在哪
Where are you?!
快走
Go!
然后他离开了
Then he left me.
挺长一段时间
For a long time.
让我一人待着
Alone.
我睡着了
And I slept.
不知道睡了多久
I don't know for how long.
然后他叫醒了我
And then he woke me up.
说要带我出去
Road trip, he said.
我们走了一半
We were halfway there when...
我才意识到
...I realized...
我们是要去我父母那里
...we were going to my parents' house.
继续说
Go on.
他把他们绑在了椅子上
Well, then he tied them up to a chair...
然后
...and, uh...
他让我跟他们说话
he told me to talk to them...
关于我童年的问题
about my childhood issues.
我就说了
So I did.
我
I...
想到什么就跟他们说什么
just... told them whatever came into my head.
你想到了什么
And what came into your head?
就是...
You know...
孩子的那些破事
just stupid kid stuff, I guess, like, uh...
我小时候  我妈妈会说我是她的小猪
my mom used to call me her little piggy when I was little.
他们丢掉我的海报
They threw away my posters.
从不培养我的自尊
Never nurtured my self-esteem.
一点点
Just slowly...
不停地
steadily...
侵蚀掉了我的灵魂
grinding away at my soul.
想让我
Trying to make me...
消失
disappear.
这并不是小孩子的问题
That's not kid stuff.
不过说句公道话
To be fair to them...
他们就是从来没理解过我
they simply never understood me.
他们完全不知道
They have no clue
我是什么样的人
who I am.
即使是我杀他们的时候
Even when I was killing them,
他们也只是呆呆地
they just gaped at me...
瞪着我
like fools.
根本不理解
No understanding.
芭芭拉
Barbara...
是杰森・列侬杀了你父母
Jason Lennon killed your parents.
不是你杀了他们
You didn't kill them.
是我啊
Yes, I did.
我捅了他们
I stabbed them...
好几刀
several times...
然后我割了他们的喉咙
and then I slit their throats.
我想走了
I'd like to leave now, please.
你不舒服吗
You uncomfortable?
现在呢
How about now?
小莱
Lee.
她突然就发疯了
She... She just... She just went crazy.
我早说那女人是个麻烦精
Told him that woman was trouble.
布奇
Butch.
可来了
About time.
打死她  布奇
Shoot her, Butch.
是吗
Oh, really?
照我说的做  布奇
Do as I say, Butch.
打死她
Shoot her.
你干什么呢  打死他
What are you doing? Drop him.
我的朋友  回忆你的训练
My friend, remember your training.
我命令你打死她
I order you to shoot her!
布奇
Butch!
别听他的  他搅和了你的脑袋
Don't listen to him. He did something to your mind.
我是你的女人
I'm your girl.
记得吗  我是你的女人
Remember, I'm your girl.
快杀了她
Kill her now!
布奇
Butch...
天呐  我做了什么
Oh, my God, what did I do?
对不起
I'm so sorry.
真对不起  我绝不会伤害你的
I'm so sorry, I would never hurt you.
-我爱你  菲什  -没事
- I love you, Fish. - It's okay.
不怪你  我也爱你
It's not your fault. I love you too.
是他搅乱了你的头脑
He messed with your mind.
不怪你
It's not your fault.
我会没事的
I'm gonna be fine.
你了解我
You know me.
再见了  菲什
Good-bye, Fish.
没事的
It's all good.
不
No!
我是哥谭之王
I'm the King of Gotham.
I'm the King of Gotham!
我是哥谭之王
尼格玛先生
Mr. Nygma.
柯林格小姐
Miss Kringle.
我注意到一件很怪的事
I just noticed something really weird.
多尔蒂警官留给我的字条
This note Officer Dougherty left for me--
每行首字母拼起来是你的名字
the first letter of every line spells out your name.
看
You see?
N  Y
N, y...
G
G...
M  A
M, a.
是啊
Yes.
真是奇怪
How, that... How-How odd.
真是太巧了
What-What a... What an amazing coincidence.
巧合吗
Coincidence?
否则还能是什么
What else could it be?
那么你完全不知情吗
So you know nothing about this?
我吗  当然不
I... Me? No.
不知道
No.
你是喜欢谜语的那个
You're the guy that likes riddles.
你笑什么  你个傻瓜  这不好玩
Why are you laughing, you fool? It's not funny.
真是个怪胎
What a creep.
她不会罢手的
She'll keep digging.
你为什么非要留下线索  为什么
Why did you have to leave a clue? Why?
放松
Relax.
她能找到什么  她能证明什么
What can she find? What can she prove?
什么都不能  没有尸体  不用担心什么
Nothing. There's no body. Stop worrying.
但她的神情好哀伤  好愤怒
But she looks so sad and angry.
我真不喜欢她那样看我
I hate it when she looks at me that way.
恐怖  古怪
Menacing and weird.
得了  这又如何
Please. Like it matters,
你和她根本毫无机会
like you stand a chance with her.
她知道你对她的感情
She knows how you feel about her
却还是视你如粪土  视你如粪土
and she treats you like dirt. Treats you like dirt.
我不管  我还是爱她
I don't care, I still love her.
听听你说些什么
Oh, listen to yourself.
有个男人样吧
Be a man!
你是个怪人  尼格玛先生
You're an odd man, Mr. Nygma.
如果她怕你  你或许更可能成功呢
You'll do better with that one if she's a little scared of you.
-别说那种话  -别打谜语
- Stop talking like that. - No riddles.
-正式投诉数次  -正经点
- Formal complaints about you. - Just keeping it real.
黑的白的  一身红的  是什么  够了
What's black and white and red all over? Stop it!
我劝你还是别辞了工作去干这个吧
I wouldn't quit your day job if I were you.
他好怪啊  好...怪...
He is... so weird. So... so...
景色很美吧
Beautiful, huh?
我会怀念这里的
I'm gonna miss this town.
你不肯改主意吗
You won't change your mind?
哥谭需要你
The town needs you.
不
No.
哥谭现在需要执法者
Gotham needs a lawman now.
不是我这样的罪犯
Not a criminal like me.
一个坚强的执法者
A strong lawman.
你说我吗
You looking at me?
得有人狠狠整顿这座城市
Someone needs to grab this city by the neck and shake it hard.
得你来  吉姆
That's you, Jim.
我深信不疑
I know it in my bones.
很多有权有势之人
There's a lot of powerful men
不会同意的
who would disagree with you on that.
这刀不错吧
Nice knife, huh?
是你父亲的
That was your father's.
他很久以前给我的
He gave it to me a long time ago.
是一时兴起送我的生日礼物
A spur-of-the-moment birthday gift.
我拒绝了
I said no.
这刀很漂亮
Such a beautiful knife,
但我有持枪的人保护我
and I have men with guns to protect me.
他还是让我收下
He said take it.
人没有朋友时  刀还会忠于你
A knife is a good friend when you have no other.
你们那么亲密吗
You were that close.
曾经吧
At one time.
这故事的意义在于  吉姆
The point of the story, Jim--
你父亲是我见过最正直的人
your father was the most honest man I ever met.
但他还是随身携刀
But he carried a knife.
别再找了  布鲁斯少爷
Enough searching, Master B.
这里根本什么都没有
There's nothing here.
你父亲是个好人
Now, your father was a good man,
虽然跟所有人一样  他也有缺点
a flawed man, like anyone else.
但他未必就有秘密生活
Doesn't mean he had a secret life.
我的直觉一向是准确的
My intuition's nearly always correct.
嗯
Yeah, well.
我觉得这是常见的错觉
It's a common delusion, I find.
阿卡姆关了一堆"直觉很准"的人
Arkham's full of men whose intuitions are always correct.
视而不见是最盲目的
There are none so blind.
视而不见
None so blind.
马尔库斯・奥列里乌斯  马尔库斯・奥列里乌斯
Marcus Aurelius. Marcus Aurelius!
他怎么了
What about him?
他是个罗马皇帝
He was a Roman emperor.
这我知道  布鲁斯少爷
Yes, well, I'm fully aware of that, Master Bruce.
而且是斯多葛学派的  我记得是
And a stoic. I think I remember he was a stoic,
我父亲也是
like my father.
卢修斯・福克斯说我父亲清心寡欲[斯多葛学派]
Lucius Fox called my father a stoic.
很多人都被人这么说过
Lots of people are called stoic.
就是怪的意思  没什么其他意义
Basically means a hardnut. Doesn't say much.
这不是什么线索啊
Doesn't mean it's a bloody clue, does it?
那是一派哲学  阿尔弗雷德  生活方式
It's a philosophy, Alfred. It's a way of life.
或许也是吧  但是...
Maybe... Maybe that as well, I suppose, but...
你觉得这是什么
What is it, do you think?
我不知道  也不管
I don't know and I don't care,
你可不许按那个按钮
and don't you dare press that bloody button.
-为什么  -可能是炸弹呢
- Why not? - It could be a bomb.
阿尔弗雷德  这不太可能吧
Alfred, that seems improbable.
是音响
It's a stereo.
[本季终]
如需其它字幕  请登陆新浪微博[WEB&BD版美剧字幕精编者]
或发邮件 lj20090303@163.com